# ANA SOUSA

## Al Research Engineer



Call me: (+351) 926 201 260

Email me: anamariaas.eng@gmail.com

LinkedIn: in/ana-maria-sousa-bioeng

Website: <u>AMfeta99</u> City: Porto, Portugal Nationality: Portuguese

#### Summary

I'm a ambitious engineer pursuing my passion and willing to improve. The ideal next step my career would be to contribute to the research/development of technologies that can improve people's lives. I really value being in an international/diverse and innovative environment that encourages the continuous development of personal skills and knowledge.

#### Work Experience



### Al Researcher & Solution Developer

Bosch | Braga, PT - 2023 - Present (1 year & 9 months)

- Connected manufacturing project (Sensors, 5G and AI).
- Understand the whole system and provide the appropriate AI algos in the filed of Audio processing, MLops, efficient Pipeline creation for AI continues learning and deployment
- · Support the SW team and develop software for process optimization/monitoring;
- Responsible for a Strategic project that aims to improve and continuously monitor production processes, using Al;
- Design and implement systems using AI/ML frameworks to meet client requirements and ensure high
  product quality. Responsibilities include tasks in computer vision, NLP, and multimodal applications, such as
  OCR and QA.

Keywords: MLOps, Abnomaly Detection, Classification, Signal Processing, Tensorflow, Keras, HuggingFace



#### Researcher

Section of Cognition, Data and Education | BMS faculty UT | Enschede, NL - 2021-2023 (2 years & 2 months)

- Domain translation of Clinical Neurophysiological research questions/needs into Data Science and ML/DL fields. This mediating capacity allowed successful collaboration of CoDE and CNPH groups, boosting the development of project and clinical validation.
- Publication of the developed unsupervised and semi-supervised deep learning pipelines for detection of EEG anomalies.
- Implementation and optimization of robust algorithm with a sensitivity of 81.9% and a specificity of 91.7%

 $\textbf{\textit{Keywords}} : \textit{EEG, Abnomaly Detection, Autoencoder, VAE, VAE-GANs, Diffusion Models, Gen AI, Signal Processing, Tensorflowng and States and States are also as a supplied of the processing of the processi$ 

#### **Assistant Researcher** (Master's Thesis)

Clinical Neurophysiology Group (CNPH) | TechMed Center UT | Enschede, NL

- Review of state-of-the-art approach for captioning in image/signal/video and Inspired on that development, troubleshooting and comparison of **6** pipelines for EEG captioning.
- Presentation and defense of the thesis before a prestigious jury composed of AI and neurologist experts, having obtained the grade of 19/20, result of excellence (among 10% of higher grades).
- Awarded for the performance in the master's thesis "<u>Learning to write medical reports from EEG data</u>." with a job position as Researcher.

Keywords: Attention models, Captioning, Classification, Video, Image, Time-series, Encoder-Decoder, NLP, Numpy, SciPy

#### **Junior Researcher** (Erasmus+ Internship)

Clinical Neurophysiology Group (CNPH) | TechMed Center UT | Enschede, NL

- Research and implementation of various data augmentation approaches, from traditional signal transformation to more complex data approach, generative models like GANs.
- · Proposing the use of different forecasting models for data augmentation.
- Provided important insight into EEG properties and behavior/potential of different approaches, stimulated further research and emergence of new projects.
- Invited to develop a master's thesis at the institution, after obtaining the Excellent grade, 19/20 in this
  Erasmus+ internship, "GANs and Data Augmentation Prediction Models in the Detection of Interictal
  Epileptiform Discharges (IEDs)".

Keywords: Time-series, Biosignal, GANs, CNN, LSTM / GRU and hybrid models.



#### **Summer Internship**

Visual Computing & Machine Intelligence Group | INESC Technology and Science | Porto, PT - 2020-2021 (6 months)

- Impact of facial dynamic fusion information & DBN in Drowsiness detector performance (AUTOMOTIVE proj).
- Collaboration with other master and PhDs students for the development of robust Drowsiness detector system to detect driver fatique.

Keywords: Computer Vision, Facial dynamic fusion, DBN, OpenCV, Scikit-learn

#### Researcher Intern

Biomedical Imaging Lab from C-BER | INESC Technology and Science | Porto, PT

Characterize lesions associated with lung cancer, using an annotated computed tomography dataset.

Keywords: CT scans, Neural networks, Computer Vision, Image Segmentation

#### **Publications**

- <u>Detection of Interictal epileptiform discharges with semi-supervised deep learning.</u>
   Biomedical Signal Processing and Control, Volume 88, Part B, 2024
- <u>Learning to write medical reports from EEG data</u>,
   Masters dissertation. Faculty of Engineering of the University of Porto, 2022

#### Education



#### **ERASMUS+ Internship**

Institution: Faculty of Science and Technology, University of Twente February 2022 to August 2022 February 2021 to July 2021



#### **Bachelor & Master in Bioengineering - Biomedical Engineering**

FEUP INCLIDENCE OF INCLIDENCE

#### Awards



#### 3rd Place - World Data League 2023

Member of the team 'CEOS'. We finished the international competition in 3rd place among 29 teams of best minds in Data Science.

#### Personal Projects & Independent Learning

This section highlights my primary interests in AI, where I have consistently advanced my knowledge and skills through self-study, Courses/ certifications. For more details, please visit my github repositories: **AMfeta99** 

- Generative AI (Gen AI)
- 2D/3D Computer Vision
- Natural language Processing & Large Language models

Final Grade: 19 / 20 (A)

Final Grade: 19 / 20 (A)

#### Relevant projects:

- TimeMetamorphy: Object Evolution Generator system powered by Al agents (ReAct, HuggingFace, Gradio)
- LM-vs.-Human-Minds: This game challenges humans to compete against LLM models in a variety of games. (LLM, LangChain, Ollama-api)
- <u>Seizure Prediction in Intracranial EEG Recordings (</u>Python, PyTorch, Scikit-Learn)
- Automated Cell Counting (Matlab)
- Brain Tumor Diagnosis App developed with Gradio. ViT fine-tuned for binary classification of brain scans (Transformer, HuggingFace, Gradio).

#### Tech Skills

- Most Used: Python, Pandas, Numpy, Scipy, Scikit-Sklearn, Tensorflow, Keras
- Frequently/Occasionally used: HuggingFace, Transformer, Ollama, Langchain, HTML, CSS, SQL, XGBoost, LightGBM, Matlab, Pytorch, Flask, Gradio
- Basic Knowledge: C, C++, JavaScript, PHP, Arduino, Docker, Multisim

#### Soft Skills

- · Adaptability, Creativity, Self-Drive
- Problem solver, Proactive, Resilience
- Empathy, Teamwork, Communication

#### Languages

- Portuguese (native)
- English (advanced)
- Spanish (beginner)
- · Dutch (beginner)